Inventory of the Abner Johnson Leavenworth Papers 1825-1850
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
{Special Collections, University of Virginia Library}
Abner Johnson Leavenworth Papers, 1825-1850.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 L48
121 items.
Papers of Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth.
Leavenworth, Abner Johnson.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence and papers of Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, Presbyterian clergyman relating to his theological studies at Andover, Massachusetts and New Haven, Connecticut and his ministry at Waterbury and Bristol, Connecticut, Charlotte, North Carolina and Warrenton and Petersburg, Virginia. Includes correspondence and accounts, 1835-1838, with Turner & Hughes, booksellers in Raleigh, North Carolina. Includes correspondence with his wife Elizabeth M. Peabody Leavenworth and a letter, 1832, from missionary friends in Turkey.
Organization
This collection has been broken down into three Series: Series 1 are the letters, Series 2 are the accounts and Series 3 are other papers.
Index Terms
Root family.; Peabody family.; Presbyterian Church--United States-- Clergy.; Subject: Presbyterian Church-- United States--Missions-- History--19th century.; Booksellers and bookselling--North Carolina--History--19th century.; Turkey--History--1829-1878.; Leavenworth, Elizabeth M. Peabody.
Contents List
  Series 1: Correspondence of Reverend A. J. Leavenworth.
- Correspondence of Reverend A. J. Leavenworth. (Folder 1-2)
  Almost all of letters are to or from A. J. Leavenworth.
  - Minerva Root, at Montague, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Montague, Massachusetts, 9 Feb[ruary] 1825. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Montague, Massachusetts to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Montague, 9 Feb[ruary] 1825. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Montague, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut 26 Oct[ober] 1825. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Montague, [Massachusetts], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Andover, Massachusetts 26 Dec[ember] 1825. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Greenfield, Massachusetts, to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Roseford, Massachusetts 28 June 1826. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Montague, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, Andover, Massachusetts 29 July 1826. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Pittsfield, [Massachusetts], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Andover, Massachusetts 13 Nov[ember] 1827. (Folder 1)
  - A[bner] J. L[eavenworth], at Andover, Massachusetts, to Minerva Root, at Greenfield, Massachusetts, 15 Jan[uary] 1828., Mutilated. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Andover, Massachusetts, 23 July 1828. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva [Root], at Greenfield, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Andover, Massachusetts 25 Aug[ust] 1828. Date changed to 5 Sept[ember] 1828 by recipient of letter, 25 Aug[ust] 1828. (Folder 1)
  - Minerva [Root], at Greenfield, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Andover, Massachusetts, 27 Aug[ust] 1828. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut, 9 Jan[uary] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - H. G. O. Dwight, at Hudson, New York, to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut. Postscript by William Chester, 10 March 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut. Postscript by Lydia Root, 11 May 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut, 3 Aug[ust] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 28 Aug[ust] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - H. G. O. Dwight, at Syracuse, New York, to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, Connecticut Forwarded to Bristol, Connecticut, 12 Sept[ember] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Lydia Root, at Greenfield, [Massachusetts] to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 16 Sept[ember] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Waterbury, [Connecticut], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristorl, Connecticut, 7 Nov[ember] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Hartford, [Connecticut], to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 3 Dec[ember] 1829. (Folder 1)
  - H. G. O. Dwight, at Utica, [New York] to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 11 Jan[uary] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Hartford, [Connecticut] to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 1 Feb[ruary] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - Susan Root, at Hartford, [Connecticut], to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 22 Feb[ruary] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - A[bner] J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, to Susan C. Root, at Hartford, Connecticut, 25 Feb[ruary] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - Susan C. Root, at Hartford, [Connecticut], to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, Connecticut, 1 March 1830. (Folder 1)
  - L[ydia] Root, at Greenfield, [Connecticut], to Rev. Abner J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, [Connecticut], 22 July 1830. (Folder 1)
  - E. M. Peabody, at Salem, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, H[artford] County, Connecticut, 6 Aug[ust] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - E.M. Peabody, at Boxford [Massachusetts] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, H[artford] County, Connecticut, 25 Sept[ember] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - E.M. Peabody, at Salem [Massachusetts], to Rev. A.J.Leavenworth, at Bristol, H[artford] County, Connecticut, 12 Nov[ember] 1830. (Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth M. Peabody, at Salem, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Bristol, H[artford], Connecticut, 11 December 1830. (Folder 1)
  - E.B. Dwight, at Constantinople, to Mrs. A. J. Leavenworth, at Salem, Massachusetts, 6 Sept[ember] 1832. (Folder 1)
  - D.M. Forney, at Tuscaloosa [Alabama] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte, North Carolina, 29 Jan[uary] 1835. (Folder 1)
  - O. Eastman, secretary, American Tract Society, at New York, to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte, North Carolina, 28 Jan[uary] 1846. (Folder 1)
    An extract from the minutes of a meeting of the committee of the American Tract Society, held in New York, 26 Jan[uary] 1836, appears on the same sheet.
  - G.A. Mathis to [Rev. A.J.] Leavenworth, 28 Dec[ember] 1836. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Brooklyn to [Rev. A.J. Leavenworth], 28 April 1837. (Folder 1)
  - S. Blanding, at Columbia, South Carolina to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte, North Carolina, 26 Dec[ember] 1837. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph H. Mather, Raleigh, North Carolina to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte, Mecklenburg, North Carolina, 12 June 1838. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte [North Carolina] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte, North Carolina, 8 Aug[ust] 1838. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte, North Carolina to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, 10 Sept[ember] 1838. (Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth N. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Charlotte [Mecklenburg County], North Carolina, 27 Nov[ember] 1838. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia, 6 March 1839. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte [North Carolina], to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia, 3 April 1839. (Folder 1)
  - A. J. Leavenwoth, at Warrenton, Virginia to Joseph Sumner, 22 April 1839., Copy. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte [North Carolina] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia, 7 May 1839. (Folder 1)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte [North Carolina] to Rev. A. J. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia, 31 May 1839. (Folder 1)
  - Abner J. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia to Joseph Sumner, 13 June 1839., Copy. (Folder 1)
    The letter includes a copy of an amendment to a contract between Abner J. Leavenworth and Joseph Sumner regarding Sumner's salary.
  - E.M. Leavenworth, at Warrenton, Virginia to A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 15 Feb[ruary] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - A.D. Pollock, at Richmond [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, At Petersburg, [Virginia], 19 Feb[ruary] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - John H. Digges, at Warrenton, Virginia to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 17 April 1840. (Folder 2)
  - John H. Parrott, at Warrenton, Virginia to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 2 May 1940. (Folder 2)
  - Simeon Colton, at Fayetteville, North Carolina to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 8 May 1840. (Folder 2)
  - A.D. Pollock, at Richmond, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 13 May 1840. (Folder 2)
  - F.J. Kingbury, at Warrenton [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 15 May 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Elisha Leavenworth, at Waterbury [Connecticut] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 19 May 1840. (Folder 2)
  - E. Leavenworth, at Waterbury, [Connecticut] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 3 June 1840. (Folder 2)
  - George Hutchinson, at Richmond [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 5 June 1840. (Folder 2)
  - John H. Parrott, at Warrenton, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 6 June 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Joseph Sumner at Charlotte, [North Carolina] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 6 June 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Mary A. Ladd, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Charles F. Wood, at Washington City, [D.C.], 23 June 1840. (Folder 2)
    Forwarded to [Abner J.] Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia
  - Simeon Colton, at Fayetteville, North Carolina, to Thomas Shore, postmaster, at Petersburg, Virginia, 27 June 1840. (Folder 2)
  - F.J. Kingsbury, at Warrenton, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 15 July 1840. (Folder 2)
    Postscript by E.M. Leavenworth.
  - A.D. Pollock, at Richmond, [Virginia] o Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 16 July 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Mary Ann Ladd, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Rev. J.N. Leavenworth [i.e., A.J. Leavenworth], at Petersburg, Virginia, 3 Aug[ust] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Henry Smith, at Hanover [Virginia] to Rev. [A.J.] Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 3 Aug[ust] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - J.H.C. Leach, at Farmville, [Virginia] to Edwin James at Petersburg, Virginia, 30 Sept[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - F.J. Kingsbury, at Warrenton, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 6 Oct[ober] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Julius A. Palmer, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 20 Oct[ober] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - D.E. Sykes, at New York, to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 31 Oct[ober] 1840. (Folder 2)
    Includes, on same sheet, Samuel G. Whittelsey, to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, n.d.
  - Samuel Lloyd ;amp E.E. Jarman, at Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania] to Edwin James ;amp Co., at Petersburg, Virginia, 12 Nov[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Kittredge ;amp Blakes, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 1 Dec[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Samuel Lloyd ;amp E.E. Jarman, at Philadelphia, [Pennsylvania] to Edwin James ;amp Co., at Petersburg, Virginia, 3 Dec[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Mary Ann Ladd, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 14 Dec[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Julius A. Palmer, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 14 Dec[ember] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - A.D. Pollock, to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, [Virginia], 12 Jan[uary] 1840. (Folder 2)
  - Henry Smith, at Hanover [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 13 Jan[uary] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - T. Magruder, at Charleston, South Carolina to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 30 Jan[uary] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - Henry Smith, at Hanover, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 2 Feb[ruary] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - William C. Dana, at Charleston, [South Carolina] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 9 Feb[ruary] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - Asa M. Train, at Milford, [Connecticut] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 25 March 1841. (Folder 2)
  - William C. Dana, at Charleston, South Carolina to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 31 March 1841. (Folder 2)
  - Alexander Mahone, at Richmond, [Virginia] to [Rev. A.J.] Leavenworth, 14 May 1841. (Folder 2)
  - E. Ballantine, at Prince Edward Court House, [Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 13 July 1841. (Folder 2)
  - A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, to Joseph Sumner, 19 July 1841., Copy. (Folder 2)
  - H. Erben, at New York to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 5 Oct[ober] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - B.M. Palmer, at Washington, [D.C.] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 1 Dec[ember] 1841. (Folder 2)
  - J.B. Townsend, at Bremo, [Fluvanna County, Virginia] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 17 Jan[uary] 1842., Copy. (Folder 2)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte [North Carolina] to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 8 Feb[ruary] 1842. (Folder 2)
  - A.J. Leavenworth to Joseph Sumner, 7 March 1842., Copy. (Folder 2)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte, [North Carolina] to Rev. [A.J. Leavenworth, 14 July 1842. (Folder 2)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte, [North Carolina] to Rev. [A.J. Leavenworth, 26 July 1842. (Folder 2)
  - Asa M. Train, at Milford, [Connecticut], to Abner J. Leavenworth, at New York, 23 Aug[ust] 1842. (Folder 2)
  - Robert A. Young, at Margaret Academy, Pungoteague, [Accomack County], Virginia to [Rev. A.J.] Leavenworth, 6 Oct[ober] 1842. (Folder 2)
  - J.N. Danforth, at Alexandria, [Virginia] to [Abner J.] Leavenworth, James M.H. Brunet, and [?] Hopkins, at Petersburg, Virginia, 7 Nov[ember] 1842. (Folder 2)
  - Joseph Sumner, at Charlotte, [North Carolina], to Rev. A.J. Leavenworth, at Petersburg, Virginia, 24 Nov[ember] 1842. (Folder 2)
  - Rebecca [?], at Salem, [Massachusetts] to M[ary] A[nn] Peabody, at Petersburg, Virginia, 29 Jan[uary] 1846. (Folder 2)
  - M.S. freeman, at Culpeper, [Virginia] to Mary Ann Peabody, at Petersburg, Virginia, 29 Aug[ust] 1846. (Folder 2)
  - Frederick J. Kingsbury, at Boston, [Massachusetts] to Miss Mary Ann Peabody, at Petersburg, Virginia, 14 July 1848. (Folder 2)
  - Mary Ann Peabody to her nephew, [?], 9 June 1850. (Folder 2)
  Series 2: Accounts of A. J. Leavenworth
- Accounts of A. J. Leavenworth, 1835-1842. (Folder 3)
  - Accounts and correspondence with Turner & Hughes, booksellers, Raleigh, North Carolina, 1835-1838., 11 items. (Folder 2)
  - Other accounts and correspondence, 1835-1842., 6 items. (Folder 3)
  Series 3: Other Papers.
- Other Papers, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Notes on the study of languages by women, and on the employment of women as missionaries, n.d., 3 items. (Folder 3)
  - Incomplete draft of a short story, n.d., 3 items. (Folder 3)
    Followed by a letter from an unknown person to A. G. M[?] asking for aid in securing a position with the South Side Rail Road.